<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-07T22:18:43+05:45</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Swapnil Upadhyay</title><subtitle>A place to let out my thoughts and musings.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Turn On Greyscale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/07/turn-on-greyscale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turn On Greyscale" /><published>2024-04-07T00:00:00+05:45</published><updated>2024-04-07T00:00:00+05:45</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/07/turn-on-greyscale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/07/turn-on-greyscale.html"><![CDATA[<p>Turn on greyscale</p>

<p>I’ve been using greyscale almost full time on my phone these days and keep it on, on my laptop it’s more of a miss at the moment. Mostly because I haven’t made it automatic (changed since I started writing this article). I just realized that these days I don’t even remember if the greyscale is even on. That’s a pretty good achievement and here I’d like to explain why you should at least give greyscale a try.</p>

<p>Our attention span is fucked. Social media has been vying for our attention. One key thing that is used to do this is color. Think about it, all major restaurant brands have the color red. All of the notification bubbles that have the color red too. The edits done to highlight the color and animations when you do certain actions. ‘What is the problem with this?’ you may ask.</p>

<p>Are you enjoying the content or the color behind it? If your attention is directed into a piece of content only because of the way that it is displayed then were you there for the content, or there because you followed the colors like a cat chasing a laser beam. This could explain why we sometimes go on twenty minutes doom scrolls and come out wondering what I did the last twenty minutes.</p>

<p>Grayscale can train our attention spans. Grayscale allows you to remove all color, and change it into tones of black and white which greatly reduces the depth of colors. This makes the screen very boring to look at. Why? Because of the virtue that all pages are optimized for color, it appears much less appealing when in grayscale. This makes us try harder to read content on the screen, instead of getting our enjoyment from the colors on it. Of course this might be different for artists, but for me, either I read the damn content on the page, or I don’t and realize that I didn’t want to anyway. There’s less distractions on there to move my attention.</p>

<p>Grayscale allows you to stop scrolling media mindlessly. Open up your app with grayscale and mindlessly binge your feed. You’ll realize that a lot of the satisfaction of the habit is gone. Taking a page from Clear’s book one of the things that makes you repeat a habit is the satisfaction you feel when you do it. Since this is reduced during the whole process you’re able to detach and make the habit less likely.</p>

<p>With that we reach the end of this one. Give grayscale a try. It’s usually better to say fuck it and not turn it off when you need to look at a picture.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Turn on greyscale]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/12/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2024-03-12T20:46:57+05:45</published><updated>2024-03-12T20:46:57+05:45</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/12/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/12/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>To add new posts, simply add a file in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory that follows the convention <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext</code> and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is iterative</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/musings/2024/03/12/life-is-iterative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is iterative" /><published>2024-03-12T00:00:00+05:45</published><updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00+05:45</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/musings/2024/03/12/life-is-iterative</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/musings/2024/03/12/life-is-iterative.html"><![CDATA[<p>Life, barring tragedy, has about 60 solid years for me. It’s easy to forget that. Everything that I work on, I can over time improve. There’s magic there that I usually forget. Anything you can do, doesn’t need to be finished in one sitting, or done in only the ‘perfect’ way. This is a trap for never really starting and the solution is to live iteratively. Everything is one experience that you can come back to improve on the next iteration.</p>

<p>It’s easy to believe that the first time you need to do something, you need to find the best, most optimized way to go about it. If you want a better body you need to get the 5 time IFBB pro bodybuilder’s routine. To learn to code, you need to find the best resources and the most optimal path to reach the goal. And in believing these, we miss out on the only thing that matters: action. Actually sitting your butt down on the chair and writing out the words. If you understand that life is iterative, you can find a lever to get you unstuck.</p>

<p>Social Media has created the anxiousness that leads to this chase for optimality. All these tiktok reels of 20 year old millionaires and instagram videos of amazing works of art. The video of their first service job, and their stickman drawing is buried under their dazzling masterpieces. This isn’t throwing shade at them mind you, they’ve worked long and hard enough to reach greatness, they can flaunt all they want. But for the average user, the digital world that shows that everyone around them is achieving so much creates anxiety within.</p>

<p>The answer then is to build on your dreams iteratively. Movies have us believing there’s this one seismic event that triggers a montage of self-improvement after which we live forever happy after. But that just isn’t true for most people, the average age of a forbes founder is 50 something. Everything is glamorized and the end product is shown but the journey is speedrun-ed. In twenty years these first works will amount to just one second of the highlight reel for those watching. Adopting the ‘I’m in this for the long haul’ is the way to go.</p>

<p>Let’s take the idea of starting this blog. Yesterday’s post was on a page that doesn’t even load, you could only open it through the homepage header. The content seems to be in .md and that makes all of my careful 7 lines of CSS moot for readability. But here I am writing another post, and fixing just a little bit of the site today as well. And on it will go as long as I can go. There probably won’t be any readers for another year, there won’t be followers of the niche blog for a couple more, and I might not be able to pass the critical threshold to reach the mainstream ever. So why worry if this isn’t perfect. Just a little improvement everyday and it’s likely that I’ll be able to get this up to snuff someday.</p>

<p>Long blog problems aside, knowing life is iterative means that you can make it a game to find a new spot to improve on every time. That maybe adding a new feature, or finding out a new macro. All the greats had their own workflows that were tailored to them. They all have their little nuggets of wisdom that they gained over the years by working on their craft. That’s something you gain only when you do the work. If you are, then doing the work anyway with an attitude of play would of course be better than feeling anxious that you might’ve missed out on the most optimal way.</p>

<p>There’s a stoic quote that goes, ‘The man who is putting the finishing touches on his life everyday is never short on time.’ That fits into this idea of an iterative life, because in each iteration your only focus is on doing what you are right now to the best of your abilities. And the next day put the next finishing touch. This allows you to not have regrets because each iteration is still done. You just add and build on top of what already exists.</p>

<p>Iteration allows you to enjoy momentum. If you think of each step as a chain that leads you to an end goal, instead of just a series of individual, isolated steps then you’re able to feel meaning by working on things. The video you clicked is not just a video, but one of many that builds into volumes. That speech is the first of many to reach greatness. Not all of it is great but you’re building on the last iteration and that makes you feel as if you’re working towards something. This is meaningful and is what creates joy in a world where everyone is unsatisfied and filling their lives with the next consumer item.</p>

<p>With every work that I’ve been doing recently, the concept has stuck. My father used to put the water bottle on the stairs leading to our room once filled. The trip would be just a minor detour. When he was done working downstairs and is heading upstairs, the work is half done and he only needs to carry it to the room. I think about those moments and smile, “iterate”.</p>

<p>(Note-I feel like Moody with how I’m preaching for “Constant Iteration!!!” (Iterative Note lol- maybe I should put in images and oooh memes))</p>

<p>You pass yourself an alley-oop when you iterate. Like the story above, every time you iterate, and then come back to it, you’re grateful to your past self for doing just that little extra. It’s self-love in how you’re looking out for future you, and that little bit of compassion starts an upwards spiral of compassionate action.</p>

<p>Iteration then is your cure for procrastination. Since each iteration can be just a little thing like filling the water bottle for tomorrow morning, or just laying out your clothes for the day before you hit the shower, there’s little friction towards actually doing it. You do just the little bit for you and the rest will be done in the next iteration. This reduces the ‘monumental’ effort that folding your clothes actually takes, and more often the compassion loop has you organically doing the whole task to help your future self along.</p>

<p>In conclusion, it’s easy to forget that you’ve got more than a couple of decades to live and that leads to a feeling of anxiousness. Even in day to day, the urge that you have to go from a zero to a hundred with no in between can lead to the sheer proportion of projects to feel overwhelming. The solution is to view it as an iterative process where you’re work is just a base to improve on the next iteration.</p>

<p>(Note- Might be best to take a shot every time I used the word iteration heh)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Life, barring tragedy, has about 60 solid years for me. It’s easy to forget that. Everything that I work on, I can over time improve. There’s magic there that I usually forget. Anything you can do, doesn’t need to be finished in one sitting, or done in only the ‘perfect’ way. This is a trap for never really starting and the solution is to live iteratively. Everything is one experience that you can come back to improve on the next iteration.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anki for internalization of nuggets of wisdom</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/anki-for-internalization-of-nuggets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anki for internalization of nuggets of wisdom" /><published>2024-03-11T00:00:00+05:45</published><updated>2024-03-11T00:00:00+05:45</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/anki-for-internalization-of-nuggets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/anki-for-internalization-of-nuggets.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="anki-for-internalization-of-nuggets-of-wisdom">Anki for internalization of nuggets of wisdom</h1>

<p>Anki is a spaced repetition software that allows users to process a large amount of information into long term memory in the most efficient manner. It is best known for vocabulary memorization for languages and for medical students for their studies. But I believe that is limiting the scope of Anki to a very small group. I’d argue that this tool is one that’s able to be utilized throughout one’s life for accelerated learning.</p>

<p>Today I’d like to talk about it’s applications for internalizing nuggets of knowledge. This is something that I’ve seen happen within my own life, but have not seen talked about much elsewhere. It all started with the idea of, “hey it’d be cool to know a few stoicism quotes.” Over a period of a few months I’ve realized that this has changed the way that I’ve interpreted experiences in my day to day life.</p>

<p>Let me tell you about an example first so it’s better illustrated in your mind’s eye and then I’ll get on with the macro level application.</p>

<p>Me and the boys who got broken up with a while back, used to talk about misery and heartbreak quite a bit. I’ve sadly not felt as deeply the ache as some others and that always sort of made me feel like an outsider. One of those days I’d gotten an anki card for a quote that (paraphrased) goes, ‘You may have emotions but you don’t need them to affect your soul.’ I’d even done the card a few times without it registering until one day when the line just connected with the experience and became internalized. Internalized in the sense that I think of the quote in my head whenever I have this conversation now, and it makes me feel as if I do have a place in the conversation. I’ve felt the emotions too, they haven’t affected my soul.</p>

<p>The sob story above is an illustration of the power of this style of anki for quotes. Usually when you do cards your brain only remembers it in that context. Only when you start to associate to other contexts do you start seeing it’s many applications. This is true in reverse as well. Even if someone teaches you a lesson unless it’s a painful lesson, you don’t actively remember it. You might even forget those pearls of wisdom along the passage of time. Anki for the purposes of this article acts as a bridge for the former case.</p>

<p>Because you have the contents of the card in the front of your short term memory, you’re more likely to remember it when you’re processing a situation or event having around you. Once you remember and associate the event to the card, the card holds more significance and is likely to be remembered in similar contexts in the future. You’re literally creating an abstraction (shorthand for you non-programmers) for referring to a situation along with the best way to deal with it. You’re also able to	 remember it better because of the deeper mental association, which is a side benefit.</p>

<p>Anki provides this benefit for a trivial cost. The input of a card even if you didn’t download someone else’s deck is trivial. Only a minute or three. If you’re batch inputting cards then that cost decreases further. Reviewing the card also only decreases as the repetitions increase. Maybe from a minute to thirty seconds to twenty-ish seconds. Since it’s a long ass sentence further decrease is unlikely. (Note- I know the purists out there will likely talk about ‘ATOMIZE mon cards’, but meh, I’ll take the hit to peak productivity with this one).</p>

<p>To summarize, with the way that we have a way to rapidly increase the frequency of hits that can occur for an association between a situation and a nugget of wisdom for what amounts to a trivial time cost, I believe getting on the anki train to go through quotes and learning them is a ‘quick’ way to acquire wisdom. (Note- Of course it still isn’t quick because there’s a need for the situations to occur, and for you figure out how to apply each of those nuggets to enough situations that it becomes an automatic response. But no one claimed that becoming wise was a three month long process)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anki for internalization of nuggets of wisdom]]></summary></entry></feed>